<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>DnD Blog</title><link href="/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="/feeds/all.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>/</id><updated>2019-08-26T00:00:00+02:00</updated><entry><title>Blog explanation</title><link href="/blog-explanation.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-08-26T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2019-08-26T00:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Stef Janssen</name></author><id>tag:None,2019-08-26:/blog-explanation.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;h1&gt;What is this blog for?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;tldr; I want to apply new techniques and it's good practice to reflect on sessions and write down thoughts about what was good and what could be better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Optimizing Dungeons and Dragons&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I like thinking about DnD, a lot. Sometimes about fun encounters, magical items …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h1&gt;What is this blog for?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;tldr; I want to apply new techniques and it's good practice to reflect on sessions and write down thoughts about what was good and what could be better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Optimizing Dungeons and Dragons&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I like thinking about DnD, a lot. Sometimes about fun encounters, magical items and NPC's but mostly about how to get the most out of a DnD session. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the most of my life I have been a Dungeon Master(DM) but for the last year I have been a player. Tomorrow I'm starting my session 0 with the party as a DM again and we're playing Waterdeep Dragonheist!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The past year has given me some time to read up. I have read a lot of posts and watched videos from &lt;a href="http://slyflourish.com/"&gt;Sly Flourish&lt;/a&gt;, the &lt;a href="https://theangrygm.com/"&gt;Angry GM&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCkVdb9Yr8fc05_VbAVfskCA"&gt;Matt Colville&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://thealexandrian.net/"&gt;The Alexandrian&lt;/a&gt;. All explain very useful techniques on how to run a better game, from efficient game prep, to rulings, encounter design and much more. The plan is to use these techniques in a thoughtful way and reflect on them in this blog.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Waterdeep Dragonheist&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm going to be running Waterdeep Dragonheist for this personal challenge with the idea to follow up with Dungeon of the Mad Mage. The modules contain a great story with an enormous amount of flavour and great npc's but the story structure and setup could use improvements. The Alexandrian has made a &lt;a href="https://thealexandrian.net/wordpress/41217/roleplaying-games/dragon-heist-remix-part-1-the-villains"&gt;remix&lt;/a&gt; of Dragonheist which restructures most of it. I will take the remix as a base and try to insert motivations for the characters for going into Undermountain after the campaign as something not yet addressed in the remix. I won't be going in-depth into either modules nor the remix, I invite you to read them all, they're very interesting reads.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;First lesson: 3 clue rule&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A large part of Dragonheist and the remix is investigation, players need to find out a lot of stuff by going out and looking for it. In order to make sure that PC's pick up important information it is recommended to provide the information in 3 separate clues. This reduces the chances of PC's missing it and doesn't make you feel forced as a DM to railroad your players into a specific clue. It provides room to improvise it into a session.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The remix provides 3 clues for the essential bits of info. But I want to include something new into the remix: a more concrete way to obtain the Red Jade Tetrahadron with which the Stone of Golor can wipe information from the world. With it, the Stone of Golor is a magical artifact with super-godly powers. As an inside joke I've converted the Tetrahadron to a Septagon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the remix the Septagon is in Dagults' possession and not much else is said about how the players can obtain it. I want to use it as a strong motivation to lure the players into Undermountain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Septagon provides a massive motivation for the players to go into Undermountain. The complications described at the end of the Waterdeep Dragonheist, where many factions are demanding the return of the money in some way can easily be solved by making them forget.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also find an early descent into Undermountain quite interesting. Dragonheist and Dungeon of the Mad Mage are quite different, but this can be fun to interweave. It will provide some variation between dungeon crawling and investigations. To make this possible, the characters need to be level 5 before going into the dungeon. Providing some earlier level-ups in chapter two seems to be the way to go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've chosen to place the Red Jade Septagon in the Heart of the Mountain in level 6 'The lost Level'. There is a temple here to Dumathoin, the dwarven god of secrets. It is in his great interests to make sure nothing can trump him in secretlore, and the Stone of Golor is more than capable of doing just that. Dumathoin has influenced his disciples to transport the Septagon to this level and into the heart.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I picked Ahmaergo, the second in command for Xanathar's Guild, to be the disciple. He is a dwarf working in a thieves' guild, and it isn't hard to imagine he worships a diety of secrets. He ran the operation of stealing the Stone and Septagon from Dagult and simply told Xanathar the Septagon wasn't there. He told Xanathar the operatives were to blame and Xanathar disentgrated them all before they blame him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ahmaergo gave the Septagon to his twin brother, Dhonmaic Silvertome, an additional member of the Fine Fellows of Daggerford, the band of adventurers that gets wrecked in the early levels of Undermountain. He starts planning the expedition and finds the adventuring band in the time between the heist of the stone and the start of the campaign.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The characters happen to be at the Yawning Portal when Ahmeargo meets with his brother as he goes down that hole in the inn with the band. This is at the start of the adventure and is the one place where we can place the clue and ensure the characters will be there to see it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Choose the character with the highest passive perception and have that character notice that twin dwarves are discussing something important and handling something that looks like a red Septagon. Before the troll sequence is started, describe how the Fine Fellows of Daggerford descend into Undermountain singing. When their voices go quiet, people all start betting whether they come back alive, and how many and how long it will take. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, when the Cassalanters become aware of the Red Septagon, they start focussing on it in addition to obtaining the gold as it provides an additional way of keeping their children. The Stone of Golor is so powerful they could make Asmodeus forget the deal they made with him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These clues can be incorporated into the reports made by the Cassalanters as well as a diary kept by Ahmaergo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another possible clue could be that Nar'l Xibrindas has been reading Ahmaergo's diary and has informed Jarlaxle of it. This could be the action that causes Xanathar to start mistrusting him, and in a whim he apointed a grell to start watching him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This way, the reports in the remix can include additional information about the Septagon, the characters were first-hand witnesses of it going down there, and the Daggerford band can answer any questions about the dwarf that got them together to descend into Undermountain, 3 clues!&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry></feed>